hello and welcome this is active
inference model stream 16.1 it's
December 6th
2024 we're here with Eli sesh And
thomaso salvator discussing divide and
conquer predictive coding so thank you
both for joining Eli to you for the
presentation all right I everyone
so um I recall being here once before
you know presenting that old paper
interception is modeling alast stasis as
control and I think at the time I even
mentioned that there wasn't really an
inference algorithm that like I could
just go and apply to all of these kinds
of like active inference and predictive
coding problems and over roughly the
last year let's say you know we've
started work this little team of myself
howo who is unfortunately not on the
stream due to having a
9-to-5 and Tomaso salvator who's here
with us you know we've actually been
working on this you know like how would
we take these theories and you know this
predictive coding idea and just turn it
into a basian inference algorithm you
can use for
stuff so you know as background like to
really refresh ourselves
this is the super short you know neurs
version of our
talk you know there's like basically
theoretical Neuroscience neuro AI or now
I don't know Tomaso like what keyword do
you guys use at verses I should have
asked you
maybe or uh we do use Nei actually biop
plausible deep
learning that's uh a sentence I often
use yeah so I think that that dates back
from even like before my versus times I
guess yeah so the broad theory is that
you know predictive coding sort of
solves two tasks for the brain and
that's credit assignment and beijan
inference now like predictive coding is
also a thing in machine learning now
they do a lot of it at verses Tomaso's
done a bunch with
it you know but it doesn't always
for various reasons we can go into like
it sometimes doesn't always scale as
well as backprop
basically and so we basically started
over again I guess you could say with
the concept of predictive coding to
build our divide and conquer PC
algorithm and we basically find that you
can use this at roughly the same scale
you would with vaes
so of course in order to you know test
it out we had this um deep latent
gausian model it's actually the same one
from I think the Monte Carlo predictive
coding paper out this
year we really did this a lot like
leaning on you know comparing to other
predictive coding papers rather than to
some arbitrary Baseline
because you know we figured
let's if we pitch this as about p as
being about biop
plausibility then we can sort
of maybe actually get results that are
good enough to
publish any yeah um so you know we
racked up our first win
there you went other algorithms that
were related or inspired us
train
really but actually
interesting
is you know basically we would say all
right you
have yeah
oh um you know after you know
demonstrating that this quote unquote
wins like okay it works well
enough the
which oh this entire slide yes
okay yeah so our dcpc in addition to
being a predictive coding algorithm is a
particle algorithm so it's training a
particle Cloud so to speak to
approximate the posterior distribution
in aian inference problem so as such we
compared it to this algorithm particle
gradient descent
pgd from which we were drawing pretty
direct
inspiration and then we also compared it
to you know lengen predictive coding out
at icml this year
and so we compared on you know the
freshed Inception distance that people
use in deep learning rather than on you
know the um variational bound to the
surprise you know we didn't compare on
log evidence because that's you know you
can often get very bad visual samples
from a model that has a very good log
evidence
actually so in order
to you know sort of say like okay that
you know log evidence is not the only
thing that counts we you know compared
on this fresh Inception
distance over here we've got some
samples from our pseudo posterior
predictive
distribution so it's a proper predictive
distribution but constructed from a
pseudo
posterior pseudo in the sense that like
we're fitting I think a small gaussian
mixture model to our big particle cloud
of the actual posterior
distribution and then having done that
we say all right now we'll draw samples
from this
GMM as a PSE suda posterior you know
then pass those latents through the
generative model again to generate
samples and you know the actual neural
architecture here is basically
a one level
vae like you just chop off the encoder
from a one level vae that would be used
in these Baseline papers use the same
neural architecture in P
torch and then basically just got you
know slightly better results
visually by just improving the inference
algorithm and the
training okay did did you manage not to
lose that
cool okay so sort of the interesting
stuff about it you know especially
compared to previous work is how this
actually
works as I said it's a particle
algorithm so we're actually drawing
samples I think I said before we went
live you know this is sort of the year
of Monte Carlo predictive coding methods
we one of maybe you know three or four
that are out this year
so after you've like initialized your
graphical model by just doing you know
ancestor sampling to get yourself some
initial you know
Cloud what you can do during you know
every inference pass is start from the
bottom up so that's you know the right
over here would be the quote unquote
bottom of the
hierarchy you can calculate you know
your prediction errors which are the
same kind of thing as in previous
predictive coding work you know there
score functions with respect to the
latent
variable and the thing that we actually
do differently from other work is that
rather than just taking like a score
function as a local gradient of the
of let's say rather than taking a score
function as like a direct gradient of
the variational free
energy we take score functions with
respect to the log complete conditional
distribution so like a coordinate update
distribution if you have you know this
variable
Z1 then it's complete conditional is the
distribution of this variable Z1 given
its entire markof
blanket so given both you know the
predictions coming in from above
it and the observations coming in from
below so that's why rather than one you
know error unit we he we have an error
unit that connects you know Z1 to the
observation below it we also have an
error unit that sort of
recurrently tries to draw Z1 back
towards its local
prior until that prior is changed by an
update at Z2
so if you think about you know how ban
inference works you know ban inference
is just what you get when you have one
distribution and it has to be
normalized but you're trying to fit it
as closely as you can to both the
likelihood and the prior at the same
time and so when you try to do that
locally within a big structured
graphical model you know the logical
posterior to go after is the complete
conditional and that's what we actually
did and I want to shout out how here
because he's not on the stream but his
previous work on advertised population
Gibb
Samplers is really what showed that this
kind of sampling from the complete
conditionals could work at
scale and you know like inspired this
project pretty
directly like this is kind of follow-up
work to you know his paper on
that and the way that we you know sort
of make this work in terms of
constructing a free
energy or in terms of making sure we
target the correct joint
distribution is that we can use Lan
proposals you know if you have a
prediction error from e sub Zer and
another you know e down sub
one add them together you have the
gradient of the log complete
conditional now it's the log
unnormalized complete
conditional but that's fine because you
know the gradient doesn't like you know
when you take a gradient of a log
density the normalizing constant falls
out and so you can Target that with you
know a Anin Dynamics
proposal which just says take your
previous
prediction you know multiply your
prediction error by a learning
rate add the prediction error to the
previous prediction and then add some
gausian
noise you know you have to balance like
the you have to balance the magnitude of
the gausian noise with the learning rate
in a certain way but like that's a
detail really it's saying let's be in
the latent space then let's follow the
gradient and then let's inject a little
bit of noise so we explore most of the
time or rather sorry so we explore some
of the time while
exploiting whenever the gradient signal
is strong
enough and then you know I note that we
use sequential Monte Carlo here and what
that's actually for is that sequential
Monte Carlo algorithms give you a whole
set of rules for how you can start from
you know the prop Al that you sample
from then go to the local
Target that you are actually trying
to you know that you're trying to sample
from and then combine those in you know
a neat way to get samples from the
Complete Joint
distribution so you would do this you
know start here from the data on the
right do this predictive coding step for
Z1 be done with it repeat the same
predictive coding step for
Z2 but now with a new prediction error
from Z1 down
here repeat all the way up here and then
you have a bunch of samples from
different complete
conditionals and you have to come up
with some way to say well what's my free
energy or an SMC terms what's my
importance weight and that's really
where
you know that's really where like the
SMC technique becomes helpful is for
proving the whole thing is
correct so if you think you know we
named it divide and
conquer because you know what we're
essentially doing is we divide the
graphical model into these complete
conditional
units then we conquer each of
them with you know basically a Monte
Carlo predictive coding
proposal and then conquer the whole
thing by recombining
them so it really is like a divide and
conquer algorithm in the classic
sense also the reviewers wanted us to
name it something clearer than the old
name all right so then you know that's a
summary of the talk really and then we
can go into like details of the paper
and you know anything else we want to
talk about
but broadly the idea here is that you
know predictive coding as a theory imp
you know enjoys biological
plausibility for approximate beian
inference which is you know actually
this really hard
task like you know in deep learning
world people use all of these awkward
neural
network arrangements to try and amortize
inference and then the people who are
real purists are just doing Markov chain
Monte Carlo because amortized inference
isn't good enough for them and to be
fair it's often not very good if you
don't you know structure your amortized
posterior like just
so and more to the point in Neuroscience
you know like predictive coding theories
have often been you know built on like
mean field
assumptions about the approximate
posterior so then you just have a
coordinate wise representation of the
approximate
posterior and it's pretty well known
that like this can't actually get you a
very close
approximation to a correlated structured
posterior so that was where the trouble
was that was the problem that we took a
first step on
solving you know and we got it to work
well enough that you can substitute it
for neural networks in some of these
cases where people use neural
networks and we're going to be at the
poster session next Friday at nups if
anyone wants to come and talk to
us you know and of course we have to
mention the places that we work and our
affiliations all right awesome thank you
um thank you I'll stop the screen share
yeah I'll I'll ask some questions and if
anyone in the live chat has questions
they can write um maybe just starting
with the
structured part what do you mean
that it's a structured
problem Oh yes so like this is the
experim you know originally I looked at
this and said well how do we actually
replicate how results from advertised
population Gibbs and that was like a
fullon Time series model in which there
were you know like some local variables
that were updated at each time step but
also some Global random variables that
were standing you know at the
hierarchical level
above so you know that was really like I
thought okay we need to tackle these
kinds of structured
problems because you know if you I mean
go look
at I'm trying to think like you know
honestly most of the time most
interesting generative models are going
to be kind of
structured if there's more than one
latent
variable and it's not just IID
sampling so any kind of hierarchical
Baye you know time series
structure dynamical system
structure like all of this stuff that
you find in cognitive science and
Neuroscience so so
commonly and yet which is often you know
we've often sort of given up on doing
anything better than particle
filtering or amortized inference if you
look in the machine learning
World okay and the graphical structure
you showed was a linear hierarchical
model or it was going from side to side
but that's just graphical convention so
do you ever need to account for
branching or any other kinds of
structures or how do you divide and
conquer when there's also splitting and
merging so I mentioned about Markov
blankets right as long as you're in a
directed A cyl graphical model then
there's still a notion of a marov
blanket for every single random variable
that's the thing that you divide you
know the graphical model into is
variables with their markup
blankets and you know this is sort of
intended to be a bit free energy
principle perhaps bringing the notebook
up would help um I'll ask the two
questions so return to them as as you
see fit the first is how do you specify
the model what does it look like before
training and what does get updated
during training and then the second
question is how do you take that step as
a model between the structure of a given
problem like the handwriting
digits and adapting that to what is that
something more generic or does that
graph need to already from some
other
source have structure that's amenable to
the
[Music]
Target so the target density that we
would try to sample from is defined by
the graphical model
structure and like that yeah that has to
come from from somewhere so
conventionally you know if you're doing
machine learning engineering then that's
sort of up to your choice as the user of
our
algorithm you know it depends on what
like domain knowledge you have about
your
application and if we were talking about
brains then that structure of the
generative model is something that
evolved you know and there could you
know and I should mention you know the
recent verses work like of course you
can also have you know structure
learning
problems you know throughout like
development
but you know throughout development and
through certain behavioral
tasks but like that gets you a bit
beyond the realm of just graphical
models and
so you know we we basically aimed at
just a given graphical model take a
graphical model as given and try to do
inference in it you can work your way up
to the harder stuff
later in practice we we often use deep
neural networks because we we try to
replicate the experiments of other
papers so we had like multi-layers and
the convolutional
models yeah maybe share the notebook
Andor the repo working up yeah yeah oh
the GitHub repo is like yeah we can
share that pretty
easily yeah going to put this first in
the zoom chat then share my screen
yeah so in the GitHub
repo we try we
attempt just zoom in a little bit that's
actually lack sure yeah
yeah so in the GitHub repo minus a
requirements file we try to share enough
that you could Hypothetically download
and run this like just from your command
line you would need you know a python
environment that's got the necessary
stuff installed but all of that is
standard
stuff so if you wanted to just rerun the
mnist experiment you would literally run
this command on your command
line and then you could also you know
start your tensor board and watch it
train you know then we include like
evaluation
notebooks that you know basically would
help you to to replicate the figures
from the
paper and Yeah we actually
have yeah we also share you know some
pre-trained like weights and
particles I know that's probably a bit
of a colliding name with like weights
and
biases in this case you know the weights
include the bias es weights would mean
neural network weights and then
particles would mean you know the Frozen
samples from the posterior distribution
for random
variables and then of course we just
give you know the paper or sorry the
table of
results and as a small bonus to everyone
else who has to try and replicate our
results we include an implementation of
the descript ized gaussian
distribution which is otherwise like
buried in the diffusion models
literature thank you very
much yeah and it's you know under MIT
licens so you know you can pretty much
go ahead and like Fork this contribute
that it's in the Universal probabilistic
programming language
pyro since that's basically like the
largest uh deep probabilistic
programming
language let's take a look at some of
the notebooks uh let's
see that one's going to look like
garbage this one's going to look like
not
garbage yeah so what this does
is you know it's basically like Pi torch
and Pi torch lightning
you know so you're going to like read
some Json
file that's going to give you you know
your data your model on your
trainer then you know you're going to
remind the trainer to just load the
weights and particles from a
checkpoint you know the random variables
are saved as part of the P torch
lightning
checkpoints
yeah it loads them blah blah blah blah
blah right there when it says
357,000 trainable parameters what is
that number coming
from that is the number of neural
network weight like that is the number
of float 64 in the neural network
weights so that's actually a relatively
small number because this was sort of a
toy problem and normally it would be
more in the
millions and where where were where were
those
combinatorics
specified uh right here in the
architecture
specification that's after it
though or yeah because you have to load
the thing to print the
thing okay okay that just printing it
out but you specified it elsewhere what
the structure would actually be loaded
it in printed it out okay
yeah the um the Json file you know tells
you like which modules in the python
code that you have to load and all of
that so if we go look at you know what
is the actual training file that we were
loading here it tells
you you know load this model
module pass it these hyper
params checkpoint this often you know
load this data
set with like this hyperparameter in
batch
size you know here's like learning
rates and the number of
particles you know the number of sweeps
meaning like passes over the graphical
model you know that you do per training
step yeah this is like um relatively
standard deep learning type
stuff yeah and when we've loaded the
architecture we actually print it
out you know so it's a simple like
isotropic gausian
prior and then we're running it through
you know a linear layer an activation
function you know a a deconvolution
layer
some batch you know the you know each
layer includes batch
normalization you know two more
convolutional layers with their batch
normalization and
nonlinearity two more convolutional
layers again and then finally a
deconvolutional layer that gives you the
correct image size and channel number
well that's
rude
anyway yeah so
then we have this method we call load
particles which just tells you that's
really for loading the particles into
GPU memory once you know which data
items you're testing
[Music]
on again like relative ly standard you
know deep
learning
stuff you know then here we
say we're going to open a python context
Handler by you know clamping the
graphical
model to the pre-trained particles that
we loaded from
disk so you know if you load your
posterior particle cloud from disk then
you have to say to graphical model I'm
testing right now don't do any
additional inference steps just use
these
samples you know as your
distribution so then we run we average
over particles to get our
reconstructions of you know training
images now we're going to plot
them here's the actual reconstructions
so like they're you know kind of blur
like you expect from a
vae but it shows that you know things
did actually
work then you say okay I don't want to
look at reconstructions of training
images you know I want to know do I have
a trained generative
model so you clear all that stuff
out and you're going to
get all of
the training and
validation you know
particles from dis for training your you
know for fitting your pseudo
posterior and you're going to predict
some new images you know using the
pseudo
posterior then lo and behold you know
you plot out the samples from the pseudo
posterior they're kind of blurry and
they're not as varied as you would sort
of like them to be
but that is what happens when you have a
very simple generative
model like you know if you go back to
this neural architecture
here this is nothing like a
state-of-the-art you know diffusion
model or whatever that you would use for
image
generation it's really just a bunch of
neural layers stuck together mapping a
latent variable to an
observation yeah and then we're
you know having generated those we go
through we calculate you know some
metrics across the validation data under
a series of different random
seeds we can also sample from the prior
rather than the pseudo
posterior and that gives us lower visual
quality but more variation more
realistic
variation and then you know we calculate
the statistics that we reported in the
paper plus some statistics we don't
report in the paper now that I think of
it like the um effective sample size
that one's a good one for inference
nerds you know you divide that by the
number of particles you're using and it
gives you a sort of percentage that
tells you
you know how well are you actually
fitting the true posterior distribution
with this batch of
samples and in our case the answer is
yeah about
92% effective
samples thanks maybe could we walk
through a similar Logic for the Mist
handwriting yeah totally uh let's see
but I think it would be almost
equivalent it's just that we use a
different
model
um yeah it's pretty much the same but
with you'll notice there's quote unquote
three decoders
here so each of these is actually
performing you know a random gussan
sampling step in between so this is a
proper hierarchical base Ian
problem so you have a
prior then you have a forward
conditional and a forward conditional so
you have three levels of latent
variables and then finally you have your
likelihood what leads you to use those
here like do you sweep or scan over 2 3
four layers do you explore out features
equals other
multipliers or what what led you to this
specification for the lightning
dcpc so in this case we took this exact
specification from Monty Carlo
predictive coding
which is over
here so like we you know we wanted to
compare inference algorithms
head-to-head so we put you know picked
exactly the same generative model
structure and you know replicated
it awesome yeah that makes a lot of
sense and it
helps with the cont uity and and
isolating the inference algorithmic
component is there
a in a methods or
procedural step
anywhere other than these or or are all
that are needed these Json configs and
the notebooks like
this so this is runnable like this
should be runable if you actually just
download it
and you know if you download it and
follow the links to download you know
the pre-trained weights put them in the
path that the notebook expects
here then you should just be able to run
this it should be point and
click I say should
because you know like I've tried it but
I've tried it
once cool definitely opportunities for
people to explore um and then what about
the training yes step
so that would be done from the command
line as the repo readme tells
us that's this
step and you watch on tensor board and
make a manual call based on diagnostics
or how else do you
determine I mean I would generally say
let it run at least for these EXP
experiments let it run to
completion like you know I know that
some if I'm stopping something partway
in because of the Diagnostics I see on
tensor
flow you know like for instance a very
noisy staticky like loss
curve well that's how I know when it's
not
working you know the experiments that
are mentioned in the paper are actually
you know known to work like you can just
leave that running until it's done and
you will get you know subject to
differences in your random number
generator more or less the result we got
in the
paper I actually want to say like this
is one of the nice things about the mo
like sort of the culture of machine
learning these days is that everything
is really expected to
be not just replicable but like idiot
proof
replicable as in if you cannot just run
this by rote and get the same result
then reviewers don't believe the result
is
real which is you know very much for
like replicability of science the way it
actually should
be so we looked at faces and digits
let's say somebody were looking at
another kind of image
classification problem
cat cats and dogs so what what would
need to be
adapted what what kind of data would be
uh in in for the training step and then
to what extent do these same lightning
dcpc specs
structures work or to what extent did
the first or the secondary layers need
to be adapted to Alternative cases MH
so this thing that gets called a graph
inside the lightning
dcpc you'd have to write a new one of
these
classes for a new problem so let's say
for instance that you want to do
semi-supervised you know beijan learning
my old adviser from my PhD had a paper
about
that you know so if you're doing say
cats or dogs then you're going to want
to specify you know a new graphical
structure that's rooted in a prior over
your latent
embedding and then it should have you
know a pair of
likelihoods essentially you know one
being to the class label which is going
to be it's semisupervised so let's say
you only get class labels on about half
the
samples and the other is going to be you
know for the actual image which is going
to be fully observed
you know and then after writing what is
it a um
a high torch lightning data module for
your data
set which like tells you you know when
which sorry it handles figuring out
which data points are semi are
supervised versus
unsupervised because it's a
semi-supervised
problem and then yeah you would put that
together and run it more Le you know you
would write another little Json
file and just run it and hopefully you
would
get hopefully if your um you know
architecture for the generative model is
Rich enough then your latent embeding
space should begin to capture you know
differences between the supervised
classes and be you know and give you
good
prediction on
classification and then if you wanted to
do classification style testing or
[Music]
evaluation you know you would present a
whole new image as the
observation and then just perform joint
Bas and inference on both the latent
embedding and the um class
label and then check that your class
labels
are good so to
speak you know for an unobserved class
lab you're not getting a one hot Vector
you're getting you know a series of
logits or like an element on the Simplex
that
specifies probabilities of class
membership so hence I saying good rather
than absolutely
correct you never get a completely
absolute yes no answer out of a
classifier at test time at
least I think in general you could also
generalize it to different kind of data
of data types so it does not have to be
for example continuous data as images it
could be you could generate discrete
distribution or you can also generate
time series distribution this is
something that that has not been tested
in this paper but in theory the
theoretical framework would allow to do
so yeah like we have an appendix in the
paper that extends the math to discrete
distributions you know that does take a
mathematical extension and then that you
know would take some more
coding so like we don't you know make
any promises
there so in in past dreams and and
Journeys Eli as you mentioned we
discussed with Dean and others the
anticipatory
allostasis and then tomasa we discussed
the
causal modeling so where where would you
triangulate this
work or how how do you see it as sort
of drawing on or complimenting or or not
but it's just interesting that it's it's
not a homeostatic model often in the
organismal ethological active inference
there's a lot of focus
on organismal behavior in these kinds of
topics homeostasis allostasis being
critical there and then in the basian
modeling space often there's a focus on
the
interpretability of smaller models and
carving nature at the joints and all of
that not this more machine
learning sort of specify
it in a sequence of convolutional
layers so how do you see all just just
having worked on those different areas
is how to each of you see I mean because
clearly this is a relevant contribution
in
advance so in in what direction or how
do you relate it with those prior
pieces I think it depends in which
direction you want to you want to push
this work a little bit forward so for
example if we look at the machine
learning side and and we want to scale
it up to larger models larger
convolutional
networks you you don't get
interpretability because because of this
method I think the same interpretability
you would have with the with with the
old algorith you have them you have them
with this one what you what you gain
apparently what this work shows is the
is that you get better
performance but then of course if you
apply if you apply to for example uh
directed graphical models or Basia
networks that have a specific hous of
structure then you can observe in that
case you have the you're able to to stay
you can do for example the the
intervention kind uh queries that I that
I presented here like a year ago or
something like that and uh but I think I
think that's not in the algorithm is
more in the kind of model you you pick
up yeah is the kind of task that you
want to solve and whether you care about
it or not so let's say maybe for
generating faces for now we did not care
about having an interpretable mod
interpretable model
what would you say answer
would um I would sort of compare it to
something like a car engine you know you
need to design a car engine of a certain
size and Power in order to put in a
certain you know in order to put in a
certain like weight class of
vehicle but that doesn't actually
determine you know whether that vehicle
is a Honda or a
Jaguar if it's the same size and you
know weight class then you can actually
use a very similar engine inside both of
them and I think that's sort of on the
one
hand the both the Beauty and the pain in
the ass of working with beijan
methods is that you know the promise on
the sticker is that here's ban methods
and you're going to solve a very broad
range of
problems with by reducing them to the
same problem which is Ban
inference and that's you know sort of
what the free energy principle is all
about is saying
it's all really just reducible to
variational inference
right but now what you do find if you go
look at like
pmdp or a lot of you know free energy
type
papers is that they'll design a model
for the paper in order to model some
piece of interesting organismic
Behavior but they'll include some real
restrictions on the expressivity of that
model which is that it has to be
solvable by something like say
variational message
passing so then there's the question of
well how do you stop restricting the
model class according to what inference
algorithm you're going to use and that
was really like the dirty secr of basion
methods that I learned in grad school
was you're always restricting the model
class to what you have a good inference
algorithm
for or at absolutely Last
Resort you know running something like
plain old Metropolis Hastings with a gou
and random walk proposal and just
waiting for like three weeks of compute
and
hoping so you know what we actually want
to do here is to say we have a better
engine like literally we have a better
inference engine you don't have to you
know now structure an entire neural
network
architecture of um inference proposals
you know you don't have to play graduate
student descent with your inference
algorithm too
much you know let's assuming that you
know brains have some kind of wondrous
generic inference algorithm that solves
so many different basan problems all at
once you know let's try to model that
and then just use it because it'll be
more powerful and more efficient than
you know customizing to the particular
generative model you
want and you know really it's like first
baby steps but it is encouraging that
you know if
you I think we show in the
table yes like we trained a variational
auto encoder you know as a baseline to
say well what if you're doing
variational inference by actually you
know training a neural network to do it
to do it for you you and it's
encouraging to show that we can do a
little bit better with like a generic
inference
algorithm that doesn't need a separate
neural
architecture you know compared to like
build a second neural network and train
it jointly with the first
one I think something that is also
exciting about this I mean at least for
me is that we like we've been we've been
working a lot with Prive coding algorith
for machine learning in and I guess you
can clearly separate them in like
supervised learning and unsupervised
learning and in supervised learning for
example you train like large
convolutional models on c for 10 C for
100 or Tiny imag net it seems that we've
kind of like hit a momentary wall so
it's up to a certain point it's becoming
really hard to scale up those
algorithms and and I think like the old
community and it's it's not only Prive
coding like when I talk with for example
equilibrium propagation pre people with
the with all the like biop plausible
deep Learning Community there's a
there's a kind of similar problem that
is a when the model is more than seven
eight layers deep it doesn't perform
well and for example scaling it up to
image net is a pain so a lot of people
are taking a step back and say okay
let's do a little bit more research to
find out why and generalize and and try
to improve the
performance in when using for example
predictive coding for generative AI so
to to generate images to sample uh data
points in an unsupervised way the first
problem that we had is that like in
machine learning we had a couple of
until like two years ago it was a mostly
a deterministic algorithm so we were
taking mostly R and Bard's version which
was the classification one there was no
stochasticity so a bunch of people
including me started publishing like
associative memory papers it's like I
give it a data set and I can uh by
giving it a little bit of information
you can regenerate exactly the same data
points and then in the last year and a
half as I said uh some people started
developing sampling
algorithms and they've been they and
basically the the papers before ours a
little bit either they do it on on mist
and fashion mist or they do it on like
colored images like CER 10 CER 100 but
they use some kind of gradient descent
so it's not a completely local message
passing
algorithm and and what we did in our
paper is that we have a local message
passing algorithm and we compare against
theirs by using basically exactly the
same architectures exactly the same
number of airx I think in some cases
even exactly the same learning rate and
things like
that as a small correction we aren't
actually a message passing
algorithm yeah like we're not
technically any form of some product
message passing no this a local
algorithm let's say yes local algorithm
yes and uh and and we do well like for
example the images of faces you've seen
may not be may not seem perfect but they
are at least from my perspective better
than
expected and the thing is we
haven't I don't I don't feel like we
have reached a wall in terms of
performance like we've tested only on
the architectures that other people have
used before and we do well and for now
there's little knowledge on how much
this can this can scale up maybe you
scale it up like two layers and doesn't
work anymore that that's something that
we we don't know yet but potentially
would be interesting to for example
something I was messaging with Eli
earlier this week is can we scale it up
to large larger decoder only Transformer
models for example not like of course
llms or things like that but for example
something that is
a like a four five
six uh layers de Transformer model that
would already be an uh
like a quite an interesting result
definitely not an easy one but I think
there is there is definitely room to
improve what's the the results of this
paper could you also maybe highlight how
how do you see local update
rules as superet
subset what have you of message passing
what differentiates the local locality
of
connectivity from something that you
would explicitly Eli call a message as
[Music]
pasted Ah that's an interesting question
I guess this a I think for message
passing you you could call like all the
belief propagation algorith or at least
basically some kind this class of
algorithms where you clearly state which
information has to be
passed from from basically one latent
variable to the other
while uh local message
passing and and they and those kind of
algorith they're all local so is a since
since you define them to be this way
they they they must have local
information well well probably if you
generalize to local message passing in
generals there are some proposals maybe
including this one in which maybe things
are not supposed to be local like maybe
you can like since it's a structured
learning algorithm you may in theory get
information from other from lighten
variables that are more far away but is
but then when you actually do the
computation they are local but that's
that's an answer I'm giving now to the
spot maybe has
a better thought on this so I would say
that message passing
algorithms differ from ours in both
their means and their
goals and really it's the goals actually
that they're starting from so that
family of
algorithms you know when when people
were working on it maybe I don't know 20
years
ago what they were really trying to do
was to get a summary of a posterior
marginal
distribution so they just wanted to be
able to pick out one latent variable for
an inference
query or a decision they needed to make
say what is the posterior on this
variable given the data not given any
settings for all the other latent
variables
and that sort
of restricts you know the space of tasks
that you can really address with message
passing and it also you know does end up
meaning that you know what you're
basically doing is some form of some
product or really integral product you
know algorithm
and that gets you all the way out to I
think probabilistic circuits are the
most current and advanced form of some
product based like exact inference
algorithm and they only support
tree-shaped you know generative models
rather than those that are you know
directed a cyclic graphs in general so
trees rather than forests
and we said well let's try targeting you
know the full joint
distribution of all the latent variables
together partly because that's the most
general form of evasion inference
problem and partially because you know
if you have something like a
hierarchical Time series model from the
active inference literature you might
need several levels of the hierarchy you
might need the Laten variables across
those levels in order to make you know
an action
decision you know several levels of
hierarchy might actually parameterize
your policy or the thing that defines
the inference problem you care about
solving you know as a
modeler that's very
interesting again to the sort of
settings that a lot of active inference
literature has tackled in these cases
it's like digit in pixel intensities Etc
digit classification generativity of
digits
out how how would it be similar or
different with something
like digit pixels
in tas's Behavior out or robot arm out
are you leveraging
this uh Identity or or at least uh
structural
congruence with the recognition in the
generativity or like a vae can you have
something different coming
in and have the output be something
that's categorically different than the
type that was used as input
like
action so I think one of the advantages
of defining anything as a basian
influence problem is that it really
changes your conception of what's an
input versus an output variable you know
for a vasion inference problem you start
with a graphical model you clamp several
variables to be observed data those
observed data are now your inputs you
know your output is any aspect of the
posterior distribution that you care to
examine so we don't have to be
outputting you know classification
logits we could also be outputting you
know yeah we could be outputting you
know
functions you know you could have say an
active inference time series module
where your agent sort of gets some
data at every step of
computation performs a full sweep over
the entire you know history of latent
variables and then and only then
actually
[Music]
um you know makes a decision about what
action it's going to take
which really highlights The Importance
of Being able to specify the full joint
distribution and then clamp down with
Nuance on what you want to be taking as
observable but kind of clamping down
from a full
joint and then just specifying and then
having an inference algorithm that will
facilitate that locally oper
operationally rather than trying
to amidst the constraints of which
inference procedures you can
perform work within subclasses of
graphical models that that abide by
those
constraint it's almost like it's a a far
cry in some ways from
2022 textbook figure
4.3 the kind of
pdps and the matrix
multiplication that it it gets
implemented in pmdp the sorts of
pedagogical
cases that do highlight
certain key
moves this
though looks and feels so much more like
a
machine learning
work and and
um it it it's um really interesting
though what this Ena you also shape the
work with respect to the venue you want
to submit to I was just going to say now
that I found when we were discussing
which experiments to to run the first
question is are we going to submit a new
RS yes and it's going to be okay then
it's going to be mostly image generation
and the yeah and also also a little bit
the venue and a little bit what did
prior work do they IM
generation we picked out image
generation because uncon you know
predictive coding networks had not yet
been used to get you know this quality
of result on unconditional image
generation
so
what other than the conference next week
what ways might you be taking
it I think maybe then the I mean
probably there are many future
directions I I guess from the from the
perspective interests me the most I
would be really curious about about
doing what what I mentioned ear about
scaling it up so for example what's the
what's the how much can we push this
kind of algorithm so a I think at some
point if we're going to have enough
compute and maybe a faster it it is this
is like some fast training but probably
like if it's implemented in a in
parallelizable library or things like
that is a you can run larger models you
can run a huge number of hyper parameter
search and and you can see at some point
where it scales up because it's also
true like we didn't do I mean yeah there
is a like we didn't do a huge hyper
parameter search at the end like we did
some but it's not but like definitely
not comparable to what standard in a
machine learning paper in which they
try in which they try like thousands of
combination of hyper parameters no we
did not do grid sweeps of like hyper par
yeah yeah exactly so so I think there's
there's room for pushing these for sure
a little bit more and May hopefully uh
much more but this is a
I think scalability is something that is
really hard to to intuitively predict
like why models work well on seven
layers and then 10 they collapse is a
you just just do it and notice that and
then I guess you can do some
interpretability afterwards and
understand the reason but doing it
before is always
a a tricky thing and so I guess trying
it is probably the yeah if you have a
method that allows you to try fast and
fail fast is the best way of scaling it
up I guess
yeah so I would also say you know based
on some of the not so publishable
results that I've seen in for instance
you know trying to replicate hous work
with like bouncing mnus
digits you know how well this works
often does seem to depend on exactly how
much
structure the generative model provides
you you know to give like prediction
errors that point in the right
Direction rather than well in exactly
the right direction rather than just
vaguely the right
direction right so you know what is sort
of how smooth versus how peaked tightly
peaked is the landscape of your like is
your free energy
landscape and when it's more tightly
peaked this algorithm seems to work you
know significantly better versus when
it's not so tightly peaked it'll often
sort of get into the region of valid
Solutions and then get very noisy as it
becomes like unable to decide which of
the potentially valid Solutions is
really the best one to converge
on you know I would say it's not so good
yet at dealing with like multimodal
posterior
distributions once a good generative
model has been learned
so they're scaling it up to that you
know I'm also interested to see like how
far could we take this on a fairly
standard machine learning Problem by
just saying you know every time we have
more layers than would be biologically
plausible to
differentiate just insert a random
variable like parameterize a gausian
right there and then just say okay now
you know the amount of gradient
calculation you have to do between
layers is biologically plausible and
will use the predictive coding math to
actually you know effectively solve like
the we'll have the random variables
substitute for back propagation in a
certain
way what do you mean by
that so if you have like a you know 12
layer I think Tomaso you said like a 12
layer
um energy based Transformer or
something so I think I think the general
concept about biologically biological
plausibility is that is a you have a
latent variable another latent variable
and you want any want the basically
Computing the gradients of the
parameters to depend on both lat
variables and not on other stuff that
are in between so for example if you
consider the function that goes from one
lat variable to the to the first from
the first to the second to be a three-
layer
Network the gradients of the weights of
the intermediate layer or of the first
they would depend on the last lat
variable and this would Mak basically
make you break the locality assumption
and biologically biological plausibility
while if you consider like a function to
be the function to be a single fit
forward or convolutional layers it means
that for every weight you have a latent
variable before it so you have a prec
neuron and a postoptic neuron actually
in practice and this will basically
allow allow you to once you do the once
you compute the gradients of the free
energy to have everything that depends
on PR synaptic and post synaptic
neurons so this is the concept with
biological
plausibility the problem that for
example I I'm noticing in in when you do
classification is that doing this allows
you to propagate the error a little bit
less regular L than backprop does
because backprop is sequential so it
shines a little bit for very deep models
especially if you have the right
activation
function so is a so I guess that's what
Eli was mentioning when he was thinking
about yeah so if you have for instance
12 if you have for instance image 12
layers
classification
right
then roughly speaking
you know the getting a gradient for the
activations of the middle layer of the
neural network depends on all the way on
the final
observation now what we'd like to say is
well how much you know ultimately like
you know it's been proved that
predictive coding in the limit
implements back propop just very
slowly but what we kind of like to do is
to calculate gradients a bit more
quickly and so what I was saying is that
you know what you could do is sort of
take the middle layer and just say well
this is going to be a random variable
now like instead of you know a single
deterministic activation that has to be
exactly right in order to pass gradients
through this is now going to be a gausa
distribution over
activations and having done that you can
then use you know our predictive coding
algorithm to say I'll try and you know
propagate through the latent space of
possible you know
weights or actually no sorry I'll try to
propagate through the latent space of
like layer
activations find you know a relatively
good solution or rather a you know
particle cloud of relatively good
solutions for those and then update the
weights in order to make you know those
activations more likely without
depending on the final
classification so depending on the
entire like backwards computation tape
of
backrop very but at the cost of being a
little bit random let's
say what's wrong with
that well nothing say probabilistic
machine Learners and say free energy
principle people and you know active
inference people but
um you know currently currently the
machine learning world doesn't like it
very much they say Bas doesn't
scale we're going to teach them they're
wrong about
that well it's super cool um if if you
have any other things you want to add
otherwise good luck with the conference
and with seing it's super exciting and I
hope people watching this go to the
repo continue on some of the
explorations that you've mentioned and
and explore it in their own ways
too yeah I mean feel free to send
questions to our email addresses that
are listed on the paper if you are not
able to get the repo to
work or if you make the repo work and
you have ideas for follow-ups yes that
too
yeah we've got a few ideas already like
you know I think I was talking to Tomaso
and saying like I've been meaning to
write some code that will allow you to
sort of pass a
deterministic output between random
variables so that we would you know not
just be able to do like graphical models
but proper stochastic computation
graphs divide and contribute
exactly
yes cool thank you
fellows till next time very much Daniel
for organizing this yeah yeah thanks for
running these like every time a new one
comes out it goes on my watch later list
which admittedly I never work through
but it they do go on it and sometimes
sometimes one or two
videos cool cool when I get the
opportunity to binge you are what I'm
binging thank you see you guys bye have
a nice day byebye